And today's דף daf is דף מ"ח. daf Mem Chet. We pick
up at the very top at the משנה. Mishnah. We had just
had a few משניות Mishnayot on the previous עמוד amud about a
house or a stone that were made for עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
You know the פשט peshat is is that they were made to
sort of serve an עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, תשמיש. tashmish. But since
the sense in the משנה Mishnah is is that as soon as
they were made, and the גמרא Gemara clarifies it, it becomes forbidden,
it forced רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot and other ראשונים Rishonim to
say that the point is that they were actually worshipped independently or
along with the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah that was placed in it.
Anyway, so there were like different stages. It was made for it,
it becomes forbidden immediately. If afterwards it was just plaster was added,
then only the plaster sort of becomes forbidden and not the thing
itself again, it hasn't been actually worshipped. If it was actually worshipped,
the גמרא Gemara says that even a house, it's a fascinating and
very major discussion throughout all of ש"ס, Shas, whether something that was
built onto the ground, you know, was it was not connected and
then built on like a home, does that a house, does that
become actually considered part of the ground? So the גמרא Gemara is
adopting the position that it actually is not considered attached to the
ground. So therefore if any of these things were worshipped they all
become forbidden. But if again it's just made for that purpose, so
if you just add the plaster only the plaster becomes forbidden, that
doesn't redefine the stone or redefine the house. And if you just
bring an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah in it or put an עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah on it again without worshipping the thing itself yet,
but then that's forbidden while it's serving that function but again will
not become forbidden once the thing is removed. But again all of
this somehow assumes that we have yet to actually worship the thing
itself or it's an interesting question about תשמיש, tashmish, right? Once the
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is even worshipped, you know, then maybe the
stone is forbidden even you know even after you remove the עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. So a lot of the parameters here are not
so black and white. But the general approach of the גמרא Gemara
is is that we're this thing is going to be worshipped so
therefore it could be forbidden even at the outset, but it hasn't
yet been worshipped. Okay and now we're going to shift to in
this דף daf a משנה Mishnah about an אשרה, Asherah, which we
which at least we assume it means although we're going to see
a debate in a later משנה Mishnah clearly is something whose identity
is not as a תשמיש tashmish but whose identity is something that
is worshipped itself and it's going to be a similar type of
a discussion. Yes Michael. You say it's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah even
in the burning. You can't get הנאה hana'ah even in the burning,
like you know? Correct. Yeah like a burning אשרה Asherah I might
as well use it for my fire. No you can't do that.
Okay so let's look at the משנה Mishnah top of מ"ח עמוד
א'. Mem Chet Amud Alef. שלש אשרות הן. Shalosh Asherot Hen. There
are three types of אשרות. Asherot. Notice everything is three three three.
Three it's a you know it's better it's easier to remember things
in threes. Okay אילן שנטעו מתחלה לשם עבודת כוכבים הרי זה אסורה.
Ilan shenata'o mitechilah leshem avodat kochavim harei zeh asurah.
Similarly to the discussion of building a house or or carving out
a stone, if the tree was planted initially to be an עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah, then that is forbidden from the moment of being
planted even if it hasn't been worshipped. גידו
ופסלו Gido ufaslo again this according to רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
all is like the position that an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is
forbidden from the moment it was made, even if it wasn't worshipped.
גידו ופסלו, Gido ufaslo,
let's say however what you did is you carved the tree
or more clearly you you pruned it and then a branch grew
you know in the place where it had been pruned. Okay so
in that case והחליף vehachalif and then you know it got some
new stuff grew where you had done the cutting so you pruned
a tree and then more stuff grew. נוטל מה שהחליף. Notel mah
shehechalif. What grew is forbidden because that's like you know something you
made, that's sort of analogous to putting on the plaster. It's true
you didn't add the stuff that grew, you just cut it and
then you sort of created the space for it to grow, you
know you sort of but that's seen as that's the thing that
you added. You're enough connected to that so again even without an
act of worship that's what you added, that is what becomes forbidden
but you didn't sort of like you know create the whole tree
so the tree isn't forbidden. So if you remove what grew after
you pruned it then you're good. But what about all the fruit
that grows? That also would be forbidden. The fruit that grew in
the place where you pruned it? No the whole rest of it.
No because you because it grows every year. Yeah that you didn't
do you didn't worship it so it only goes again all of
this assumes you haven't worshipped it. The גמרא Gemara will get to
the question of what if you worshipped it. But if you haven't
worshipped it it's only the stuff that you created. העמיד תחתיה עבודת
כוכבים ונטלה, He'mid tachteyha avodat kochavim venatlah,
let's say you actually very parallel to the other cases you just
put an idol underneath it so you haven't you know worshipped the
tree itself so הרי זה מותר harei zeh mutar so it's permissible
once the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is removed but presumably not while
the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is there. Are we worshipping the עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah or worshipping the tree? No in the third case
you're not, in the third case that's the shift and it's similar
to like the other cases. That's what רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
say about the other cases as well. It shifts from the first
two being about the thing itself being the object of worship to
just housing or you know being serving the object of worship and
therefore and you didn't do anything to the thing itself so the
whole thing is only ad hoc forbidden, once you remove it you're
fine.
Okay so the tree is still considered a תשמיש. tashmish. Is providing
shade for it? In other words, what's a tree doing if you
put עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? While the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is
there, yeah, it's a תשמיש. tashmish. Okay? Now, but the question is
why is it, is it forbidden even before you've worshipped the object,
right, like the similar by the case of the house and by
the case of the of the platform, right, it sounds like while
it's still there, it's forbidden. Now why? If you've actually worshipped the
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, then it should remain forbidden even afterwards. It
became a תשמיש. tashmish. If you haven't, why is it forbidden while
it's there? So some ראשונים Rishonim sort of say it's more like
a דרבנן de-Rabbanan in that case, like, you know. Anyway, let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר דבי רבי ינאי, Amar d'bei
Rabbi Yannai, they said in the house of רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai,
והוא שהבריך והרכיב בגופו של אילן, ve-hu she-hivrich ve-hirkiv be-gufo shel ilan,
similar to what we said yesterday, right, our statement of רב אמי,
Rav Ammi, that it's not enough that you actually lopped it off
and something grew in its place. You have to actually have added
the thing on in the middle case of the גמרא. Gemara. You
actually have to have grafted on a branch. Okay, but presumably if
you didn't graft on a branch, you just lopped and something grew
and again you didn't worship it, then this would be saying, and
this is a reasonable position, you didn't add the stuff that grew
afterwards, so that's not forbidden. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says והנן
גידו פיסלו תנן, ve-hanan gido pislo tnan, but okay, logically that might
make sense, but the משנה Mishna says that just a pruning it,
it doesn't say and the stuff that grows afterwards, it doesn't say
you have to actually graft onto it. Okay? והנן גידו פיסלו תנן
אלא כי אתמר דרבי ינאי, ve-hanan gido pislo tnan ela ki itmar
de-Rabbi Yannai, okay, you're right. So it's a nice פשט, pshat, but
it doesn't fit the משנה. Mishna. So what was the context of
רבי ינאי? Rabbi Yannai? לענין ביטול אתמר, le-inyan bittul itmar, not regarding
the new stuff that's grown that's forbidden, but regarding what you have
to do, or the non-Jew rather, what the non-Jew has to do
in order to make it all permissible. Okay? דאף אגב דהבריך והרכיב
בגופו של אילן, de-af agav de-hivrich ve-hirkiv be-gufo shel ilan, we had
just something just like this yesterday about adding plaster and getting into
the nooks and crannies. That even in that case, it doesn't redefine
the entire stone. It's only the plaster that was added and only
the plaster that has to be removed. So here too, even if
something is grafted onto the tree, it doesn't redefine the whole tree.
And therefore, it's only an act was done on that thing that
was grafted, and it's sufficient to remove that thing. Okay? ואף אגב
דהבריך והרכיב בגופו של אילן, ve-af agav de-hivrich ve-hirkiv be-gufo shel ilan,
even though you grafted onto the actual tree itself, כי נטל מה
שהחליף שפיר דמי, ki natal mah she-hechlif shapir dami, just remove what
you added and that's fine. It does not redefine the entire tree.
Again, all these are cases presumably you didn't worship the tree, so
the whole issue that it was that it was made for that
purpose. Okay? And therefore it focuses on what you added and what
you made. Now,
מהו דתימא, mahu de-teima, and I might have thought that I just
write that. Do you see that? Yeah, כיון דהבריך והרכיב בגופו של
אילן כמאן דנטעו מתחילה דמי, keivan de-hivrich ve-hirkiv be-gufo shel ilan keman
de-nata'o mi-techilla dami, it's since you actually grafted on to it, it's
like you planted the whole tree, it's like you redefined the whole
tree, וליסר כולה, ve-leisar kulei, and it's all forbidden, קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that no, it's just what you added. Fine. Okay?
And as I've been saying five times now, it's only assuming you
didn't worship it. If you worshipped it, then you don't have to
do anything, well, certainly in the house you don't have to do
anything assuming that the house is not considered מחובר. mechubar. Okay? The
other things, the tree, it's not so clear what would happen if
you worshipped it because it is considered מחובר. mechubar. So maybe maybe
worshipping it wouldn't be enough. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to get to. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, המשתחוה לאילן, ha-mishtachaveh le-ilan,
if somebody bows down to a tree,
תוספתיה אסורה. toseftia asura. So he takes a middle position, and this
might remind you of a discussion earlier of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
and the רבנן, Rabbanan, and we're going to try to fit it
into that debate in a minute. He says if since it's all
growing from the ground and so on, it's like the mountaintop, you
can't make the tree itself forbidden if you worship it, but you
can make what grows afterwards forbidden. Okay? If you might remember before,
that was how the גמרא Gemara assumed that that was a position
of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda. Okay? Now שמואל
Shmuel is saying it.
So the fruit that grew after would be forbidden.
Okay? מתיב רבי אלעזר, Metiv Rabbi Elazar, now רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
challenged שמואל Shmuel based on our משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna says
גידו פיסלו gido pislo לעבודת כוכבים, la-avodat kochavim, if you pruned it
for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah והחליף, ve-hechlif, and then something grew, נוטל
מה שהחליף. notel mah she-hechlif. So the problem is what grows afterwards.
Okay?
Now, גידו פיסלו אין, gido pislo in, it's only there's only a
problem by what grows afterwards if you pruned it. Okay? לא גידו
פיסלו לא, lo gido pislo lo, if you didn't prune it, then
even what grew afterwards would not be a problem. Now the easy
answer would be similar to what the גמרא Gemara said before about
the house and what I've been saying until now, that the משנה
Mishna is talking not in a case where you didn't worship it
yet. Right? If you remembered yesterday, that was a point about the
house. Okay? And the גמרא Gemara could have said that. תוספות Tosfos
actually wants to know why the גמרא Gemara didn't say that. Okay?
So one way to have dealt with this problem, why does the
משנה Mishna need you to prune it, why isn't worshipping it enough,
is to say we're talking we're not talking about a scenario that
you worshipped it. We're just talking about a scenario that you pruned.
But the גמרא Gemara is going to push it even further. No,
maybe our משנה Mishna is talking about that you worshipped it. So
why in the משנה Mishna do you need to actually prune it,
שמואל Shmuel says you don't need to prune it? So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר לך שמואל הא מני רבנן היא, Amar lach Shmuel
ha mani Rabbanan hi, ושמואל דאמר כרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, u-Shmuel de-amar
ke-Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda, שמואל Shmuel would say to you that is
the that is the רבנן, Rabbanan, the רבנן Rabbanan say that when
you worship a tree, you don't make it forbidden, even the stuff
that grows further. So according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, right, you need
to actually both prune it and worship it. תוספות Tosfos actually discusses,
maybe you need both in this case. Okay? Because just worshipping a
tree that grows would not make it and wouldn't even make the
stuff that grows after. That is the, that is the rabbis. The
rabbis say that when you worship a tree, you don't make it
forbidden, even the stuff that grows afterwards. So according to the rabbis,
right, you need to actually both prune it and worship it. תוספות
Tosafot actually discusses maybe you need both in this case, okay, because
just worshipping a tree that grows would not make it and wouldn't
even make the stuff that grows afterwards forbidden. Okay, that's considered just
part of the landscape. When I say worshipping it is enough, you're
right, I'm not going like the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah needs
you also to prune it. I'm going like רבי יוסי בר רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda says that a tree that was planted, again
not let's say a tree that grew wild in a forest, you
have enough sort of control over that your act of worshipping makes
what grows forbidden. Okay, like we had in earlier debate. So he's
actually saying our משנה Mishnah that worshipping is not enough is going
like the רבנן. Rabbanan. By the way, a little parenthetical point, it's
a little interesting because שמואל Shmuel would say to you that שמואל
Shmuel says like רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi
Yehuda. So it's clear the שמואל Shmuel would say to you is
the גמרא Gemara speaking for שמואל, Shmuel, like it doesn't say שמואל
Shmuel would say to you I say like רבי יוסי בר רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda. So רש"י Rashi actually points that
out. If you look at רש"י Rashi אמר לך שמואל Amalakh Shmuel
about 15 lines down from the narrow lines, he
says
תלמודא מהדר הכי מצי שמואל לתירוציה. Talmuda mahadar hachi matzi Shmuel l'tirutzei.
The תלמוד Talmud is speaking on behalf of שמואל, Shmuel, telling you
שמואל Shmuel would be able to say the following. So that's always
the case, but it's nice to sort of see רש"י Rashi spell
that out explicitly. Sometimes in ישיבה Yeshiva they lose sight of that,
you know, that where it says oh רב הונא Rav Huna would
say this and רב נחמן Rav Nachman would say this and it's
really the גמרא Gemara is speaking on behalf of them. It's not
actually what they said. Okay, so anyway, so according to this, our
משנה Mishnah is talking even if you worshipped it, but this is
a tree, it's growing, it's part of the landscape. It doesn't make
it forbidden by worshipping it. שמואל, Shmuel, however, says like רבי יוסי
בר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda that it does make
it forbidden, at least the stuff that grows afterwards. Okay, דאמר אילן
שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו De'amar ilan she'nata lo l'sof avdo
that if a tree that was at least initially planted, maybe if
it was wild it would be different, and then it was worshipped,
אסור Assur forbidden. Okay, now what we're going to do, that's a
nice read, and that has שמואל Shmuel going like one תנא Tanna
in a position. But now what we're going to do is we're
going to suggest a different read of the whole רבי יוסי בר
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda and the רבנן Rabbanan debate.
Okay, which is going to make everybody sort of stricter than we
thought. Everybody's going to up them one notch. Okay, so
מתקיף לה רב אשי. Maskif lah Rav Ashi. So רב אשי Rav
Ashi challenges. ממאי דרבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה ורבנן בתוספתא פליגי? Mimay
d'Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbanan b'Tosefta pligi? What makes you think
that the whole debate of רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei
bar Rabbi Yehuda and the rabbis is whether your act of worshipping
a tree makes the additional stuff forbidden or not and everybody agrees
that the base remains permitted? Right, that's what we've been assuming. דילמא
תוספתא דברי הכל אסור. Dilma Tosefta d'virei hakol assur. Let's up it
a notch. Let's
say דילמא תוספתא דברי הכל אסור. Dilma Tosefta d'virei hakol assur. Everybody
agrees the new stuff that grew is forbidden because that's after your
act of worship, that's new, that's seeming as though, you know, even,
you know, maybe you didn't, maybe you didn't plant it, maybe you
know it's enough that you, it relates to you, it's not like
it already pre-existed. Everybody would agree the new stuff is forbidden. ובעיקרו
פליגי. Uve'ikaro pligi. And what they're debating is whether you can make
the pre-existing stuff forbidden. Okay, רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei
bar Rabbi Yehuda would say if you worship it, you make the
whole tree forbidden. By the way, just parenthetically, it actually did sound
like that earlier in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara tried to
say he's only making the new stuff, but earlier quotes in the
גמרא Gemara made it sound like he says the whole tree is
forbidden. So let's say that. Let's say everybody agrees the new stuff
is forbidden and the whole debate is whether the old stuff is
forbidden. That this is like חדש אסור מן התורה. Chadash assur min
haTorah. What do you mean? I don't understand. Oh, I see. דרבי
יוסי בר רבי יהודה סבר עיקרו נמי אסור, De'Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi
Yehuda savar ikaro nami assur, even the, even the root, you know,
even the base, what was pre-existing is forbidden. דכתיב De'chtiv it says
ואשריהם תשרפון באש. V'asheireihem tisrefun ba'esh. So what's the proof of that?
So רש"י Rashi says the proof is or the hanging, the support
is the double language of ואשריהם V'asheireihem in plural. So it means
two types of אשרות, Asheras, whether you planted it initially or whether
it was already planted and you worshipped it, you destroy the whole
thing. So רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda
says yeah, even if you worshipped it after it was growing, you
destroy the whole thing. That's considered תפיסת יד אדם. Tfisas yad adam.
רבנן סברי לא, עיקר אילן שרי. Rabbanan savri lo, ikar ilan shari.
The base, if you worshipped it after it was growing, the base
remains permissible. דכתיב De'chtiv it says ואשריהם תגדעון. V'asheireihem tigadun. That's the
verse of hewing it down, chopping it down, which means that suggests
that the base is allowed to remain. Okay, איזהו אילן שגידועו אסור
ועיקרו שרי? Eizehu ilan she'gidu'o assur v'ikaro shari? Which would be a
tree that the base is forbidden but, I mean that the stuff
you chopped down is forbidden but the base is permissible? So הוי
אומר אילן שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו. Hevei omer ilan she'neta lo l'sof avdo.
That would be a tree that was planted and then you worshipped.
So what we said before of רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda, everybody gets upped one notch. What we said
before רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda is
now the רבנן. Rabbanan. The רבנן Rabbanan admit that the new stuff
is forbidden, it's the base remains permissible. And רבי יוסי בר רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda says it's all forbidden. And if
you say now, of course by saying that,
okay, that then we got now a problem because now we've got
our משנה. Mishnah. Who's our משנה Mishnah going to go like? Why
does our משנה Mishnah need you to actually to prune it? Okay,
so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
וכי תימא הדר לא מתרצינן הכי. V'chi teima hadar lo matretzinan hachi.
So now if you say that, oh, the reason we didn't explain
that was איפכא רבנן לרבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה רבי יוסי בר
רבי יהודה לרבנן Ipcha Rabbanan l'Rabbi Yosei bar Rabbi Yehuda Rabbi Yosei
bar Rabbi Yehuda l'Rabbanan that if we basically like you know reverse
the positions of them, it's not exactly reversing, everybody's being upped a
notch. But that if basically if we sort of have them use
the פסוקים Psukim in the different ways than we had them use
them before. אם כן גידו פסלו מאן תנא ליה. Im ken gidu
pislo man tana lei. So if you'll say okay we could have
explained their debate like that, but then we've got a problem. If
everybody says that the new stuff is forbidden, who's our משנה Mishnah
going to go like? Our משנה, Mishnah, right, requires you to you
know, it's good that שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel* now goes like the רבנן
Rabanan *Rabbanan* because שמואל *Shmuel* says the base is permissible and the
new stuff is forbidden. Now שמואל *Shmuel* isn't just like a דעת
יחיד *daas yachid* of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi... ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi
Berabbi Yehuda*, but what does our משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* require you to
prune it? Right? Everybody should say that worshipping it makes the new
stuff forbidden. מאן קתני לה לא רבנן Rabanan ולא רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi בר יהודה *man katni la lo Rabbanan velo Rebbi Yosi bar
Yehuda*. It's not the רבנן Rabanan *Rabbanan*, it's not רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda*. אי רבנן Rabanan *ei Rabbanan*,
if it's the Rabbis, בלא גידו פיסולו נמי תוספת אסור assur, *belo
gido pisulo nami tosafas assur*. Just worshipping it without pruning it, the
new stuff is still forbidden. אי רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi ברבי יהודה
*ei Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda*, and if it's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi,
ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda*, עיקר אילן נמי אסור assur *ikar
ilan nami assur*. So then it's even more than that, even without
pruning it the whole tree is forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, so that maybe that's why we, it forced us to frame
the debate that it was one notch lower, that the רבנן Rabanan
*Rabbanan* actually said that even the new stuff isn't forbidden and that's
why the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* requires you to prune it and the
משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* and שמואל *Shmuel* is like a דעת יחיד *daas
yachid*. So that's maybe why, but we'd rather maybe have שמואל *Shmuel*
go like everybody and but then what are you going to do
with the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, I
have a way to deal with the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*. The גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says like this: איבעית אימא רבנן Rabanan ואיבעית אימא רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi ברבי יהודה *ibayis eima Rabbanan ve'ibayis eima Rebbi Yosi
Berabbi Yehuda*. I can tell you what, I can say everybody is
one notch higher and I can make the משנה *Mishnah* work, whether
according to the רבנן Rabanan... *Rabbanan* and I'll even take you on
your challenge, I'll even make it work according to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda*. How you going to do
that? Let's take a look. Okay, איבעית אימא רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
איבעית אימא רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei ברבי יהודה *ibayis eima Rebbi Yosi
ibayis eima Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda*. So let's start even with the
harder one, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi, ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda*
that says the whole tree is forbidden. So why does the משנה
*Mishnah* require you to prune it? So כי אמר רבי יוסי Rebbe
Yosi, ברבי יהודה בלא גידו פיסולו עיקר אילן אסור assur? *ki amar
Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda belo gido pisulo ikar ilan assur*, when does
he say without pruning it that even the whole base of the
tree is forbidden, everything is forbidden,
בסתמא *bistama*,
that's if in a normal case, meaning meaning if you just worshipped
it, the whole tree is forbidden. But I might think that if
you pruned it and then worshipped it, maybe actually you would have
then not maybe, you would actually make that it would limit the
forbidden, it would make it less severe. Why would it make it
less severe? You did something more. From the one hand you did
something more, but on the other hand your action demonstrates the focus
of your worship. Okay. אבל גידו פיסולו *aval gido pisulo*, but once
you actually pruned it, גליא דעתיה *galya daatei*, you have revealed your
intention דבתוספתא ניחא ליה בעיקרא לא ניחא ליה *de b'tosasfta nicha lei
be'ikara lo nicha lei*, you're focusing on the new stuff, you're not
focusing on the base. So the משנה *Mishnah* could actually work very
nicely according to רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi Berabbi
Yehuda*. The חידוש chiddush. *chiddush* of the משנה *Mishnah* is not that
you need to prune it, the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of the משנה
*Mishnah* is if you סתם *stam* worshipped it, the whole thing is
forbidden. Okay. It's a little funny though, the beginning of the משנה
*Mishnah* talks about planting it, the beginning of the משנה *Mishnah* could
have just said you worshipped it, but okay, worshipping or planting it,
the whole tree is forbidden. If you prune it, only the new
stuff is forbidden, it focuses your your worship. Okay. That's רבי יוסי
Rebbe Yosi ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda*. ואיבעית אימא רבנן Rabanan
*ve'ibayis eima Rabbanan*, and if you and if you pruned in that
spot but not the rest of the tree? Yeah. Or yes. And
if you and if you prune, yeah, right, or the new branch
that grows in the place. איבעית אימא רבנן Rabanan? *ibayis eima Rabbanan*,
now how about the רבנן Rabanan *Rabbanan*? According to the רבנן Rabanan;
*Rabbanan*, you don't need pruning, it's always just the new stuff. So
still, why is the משנה *Mishnah* mentioning pruning? איבעית אימא רבנן Rabanan.
*ibayis eima Rabbanan*, איצטריכא ליה *itzricha lei*, no, it's telling you obviously
you don't need pruning. If you just worshipped it, just the new
stuff would be forbidden. But it's telling you even if you pruned
it, it doesn't make anything more forbidden. סלקא דעתך אמינא כיון דעביד
ליה מעשה בגופיה עיקר אילן נמי ליתסר *salka daatach amina keivan de'avid
lei maaseh begufei ikar ilan nami litzor*, since you're doing an act
to the tree itself, maybe in this case the Rabbis would say
the whole tree becomes forbidden. Sure, just the addition is forbidden even
if you didn't do any act. Maybe with an act everything is
forbidden. קא משמע לן *kamashma lan*, not that way, that the pruning
of it does not make it worse. So again, it's not like
you need the pruning of it. For שמואל *Shmuel* the whole tree
would be for I mean for רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi ברבי יהודה
*Rebbi Yosi Berabbi Yehuda* the whole tree would be forbidden without the
pruning, the pruning actually doesn't make it forbidden makes less of it
forbidden, just the stuff you pruned. And for the רבנן Rabanan. *Rabbanan*,
just the additional stuff would be forbidden and the חידוש chiddush *chiddush*
is even with pruning it's just the additional stuff. So bottom line
is the משנה *Mishnah* could be talking about the whole debate like
we said earlier, that it was about the additional stuff. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* now is saying actually you could up the debate one.
And you could say everybody agrees the additional stuff that allows שמואל
*Shmuel* who says the additional stuff is forbidden to be the רבנן
Rabanan *Rabbanan*, not רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi Berabbi
Yehuda*, not a דעת יחיד *daas yachid*. Okay. Everybody agrees additional stuff.
The debate is the base stuff. Why then does the משנה *Mishnah*
need you to prune it? It doesn't really need you to prune
it.
Because pruning may make it better or worse, basically. Right. But either
way there's a חידוש chiddush *chiddush* in saying it, but it's not
necessary. Okay. Now so that was a nice revising or reassessing of
the debate of רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi; ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yosi Berabbi
Yehuda* and the רבנן Rabanan *Rabbanan*. To the end of the day
we don't really know. Right. Exactly. Now let's take a look at
the next משנה *Mishnah*. Okay. So remember, in our משנה *Mishnah* the
first two cases presumed you were worshipping the tree itself, and the
third case is you just put an idol under the tree. Now
we're going to see that that actually how you think of an
אשרה Asherah *Asherah* in general is actually a debate. איזו היא אשרה
*eizu hi Asherah*? You know, when the תורה *Torah* says chop down
their אשרות *Asherahs*, what is it talking about? Good question. כל שיש
תחתיה tachteha. עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim *kol sheyeish tachatei avodas kochavim*. So
one opinion is even if you didn't worship it itself, even if
it just has an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *avodah zarah* under it.
Which raises interesting questions because since the משנה *Mishnah* says Just take
away the idol, why does the תורה *Torah* tell you you have
to destroy it? Right? Very bizarre. Okay. Maybe, maybe again, the משנה
*Mishnah* is talking about they have yet to worship the idol, but
it's very bizarre. It doesn't explain that. רבי שמעון אומר כל שעובדין
אותו *Rebbe Shimon omer kol she'ovdin oso*. No, no, no, you worship
the thing itself, okay? And that's why you have to destroy it.
ומעשה בצידן *U'maiseh b'Tzidon*, and now there's a story in the case
of Tzidon, אילן שהיו עובדין אותו *ilan she'hayu ovdin oso*, they would
worship a particular tree, ומצאו תחתיו גל *u'matzu tachtov gal*, and they
found underneath it like a pile of rubble. אמר להן רבי שמעון
*Amar lahen Rebbe Shimon*, so Rebbe Shimon said, בדקו את הגל הזה
*bitku es hagal hazeh*, go check the pile of rubble הזה *hazeh*,
see what you can find. ובדקו ומצאו בו צורה *U'batku u'matzu bo
tzurah*, and they found that under that pile there was some image
of some idol. אמר להן *Amar lahen*, הואיל ולצורה הן עובדים נתיר
להן את האילן *hoyl u'l'tzurah hein ovdim natir lahen es ha'ilan*. So
he said, it's so that when it says that they worship the
tree, it obviously doesn't mean you saw them—you knew that they were
worshipping the tree. You saw them going there and doing pagan worship.
So the question was: were they worshipping the tree or were they
worshipping the idol? So רבי יוסי בר יהודה *Rebbe Yose bar Yehuda*
said—look, not רבי יוסי *Rebbe Yose*—רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon* said, since we
found an idol, we're going to assume they worshipped the idol and
not the tree, and therefore the tree is okay. It's like the
case in the previous משנה *Mishnah*. So according to him, the only—what
he's saying—now the question is, so when does the תורה *Torah* ever
tell you to destroy an אשרה *asherah*? So what he probably, you
know, so it sounds like he's actually—so anyway, it's not clear. One
could surmise what he is saying is, is that—I mean, Rebbe Shimon
at least makes sense. He's saying that the only real case in
the תורה *Torah* of the אשרה *asherah* is when they worship the
tree itself, right? Any time that they just worship the idol, it's
not really an אשרה *asherah*. It actually fits nicely into the previous
משנה *Mishnah*. But the רבנן *rabbanan* who seem to say that an
אשרה *asherah* is when you just worship the idol, so why does
the משנה *Mishnah* seem to, you know, that that's sufficient to make
the tree forbidden, why does the previous משנה *Mishnah* seem to say
just remove the idol and you're okay? Not clear. Let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. איזהו אשרה *Eizehu asherah*? What's an
אשרה *asherah*? ואנן שלוש אשרות תנן *Ve'anan shalosh asheros tnan*. But what
do you mean, what's an אשרה *asherah*? The משנה *Mishnah* בפירוש *b'ferush*
tells you about an אשרה *asherah*. It gives you two scenarios in
which it's—the thing is worshipped, and in a third scenario in which
they just worship the idol. So what do you mean, what's an
אשרה *asherah*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הכי קאמר שתיים לדברי
הכל ואחת מחלוקת רבי שמעון ורבנן ve-Rabanan? *Hachi ka'amar, shtayim l'divrei hakol
v'achas machlokes Rebbe Shimon v'rabbanan*. The first two everybody agrees. If you
worship the thing itself, nobody disagrees that that's an אשרה *asherah*. The
last case where you just worship the idol is a debate of
Rebbe Shimon and the רבנן *rabbanan*. So that you didn't worship the
tree is a debate of Rebbe Shimon and the רבנן *rabbanan*. So
that makes it sound, right, that the previous משנה *Mishnah* was going
according to רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon*, right? Because according to the רבנן
*rabbanan* it sounds like even if you just worship the idol, the
tree itself becomes forbidden, and it doesn't become permissible when you remove
the idol. Very unclear. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* never really fully connects
the dots, but that's certainly what it sounds like, that the previous
משנה *Mishnah* is a רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon* משנה *Mishnah*. Okay. איזהו
אשרה שנחלקו בה רבי שמעון וחכמים *Eizehu asherah she'nechelku bah Rebbe Shimon
v'chachamim*? כל שיש תחתיה עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim, *Kol she'yesh tachteha avodas
kochavim*. If the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *avodah zarah* is under it
but they don't worship the tree itself. רבי שמעון אומר כל שעובדין
אותו *Rebbe Shimon omer kol she'ovdin oso*. Okay. And no, it's—you have
to actually worship the tree itself. If you just worship the idol,
the tree itself does not become forbidden. So it actually does sound
like the previous משנה *Mishnah* is רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon*. Okay. And
then if you just worship the idol, you do not make the
tree forbidden in any permanent way. That's certainly what it
sounds like. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אשרה
סתם *Asherah stam*. This is not now explaining our משנה *Mishnah*, it's
just saying a סתם *stam* case. What type of a tree should
we presume is an אשרה *asherah*? Okay. It doesn't tell us according
to whose definition,
but let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* answers. אמר רב כל
שכומרים יושבין תחתיה ואין טועמין מפירותיה *Amar Rav, kol she'komarim yoshvin tachteha
v'ein toamin mipairosah*. Any type of a tree that the—you see
priests—it's treated as like a holy tree. You see it's like a—you
know, it doesn't mean that priests—every—you know, like there's a forest and
sometimes they go to a forest—I mean, I don't think it means
that they randomly sit underneath it. I think it means like it's
a place where they particularly choose to sit. And at the same—on
the one end, they particularly choose to sit there, and at the
same time they don't eat the fruit. So the combination of those
two factors tells you it's probably an אשרה *asherah*. Now again, whose
אשרה *asherah*? The חכמים *chachamim*'s אשרה *asherah*, רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon*'s אשרה
*asherah*? I don't know. Okay. ושמואל אמר אפילו אמרו הני תמרי לבי
נצרפי אסור *U'shmuel amar, afilu amru hani tamri l'vei nitzrafi asur*. דרמי
בי שכרא ושתי ליה ביומי דם *D'rami bei shichra v'shasi lei b'yomei
dam*. Now this to me seems like a rabbinic extension of the
idea. I really don't understand this at all fitting into the previous
definitions. He says even if you just hear the priest say, "We're
going to use these dates that come from this tree לבי נצרפי
*l'vei nitzrafi*," which רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says basically is the name of
an idol. Okay. It's forbidden. Why? Because what they're going to do
is they're going to take those dates and turn it into beer
and they're going to drink it on their holiday. So I don't
get it. According to שמואל *Shmuel*, it's a type of a tree
that supplies, you know, fruit that's going to be used in their
עבודה זרה avodah zarah *avodah zarah* purpose. That's not an אשרה *asherah*.
You know, it's not even an אשרה *asherah* according to the חכמים
*chachamim*. It's not a direct תשמיש *tashmish* of an עבודה זרה avodah
zarah *avodah zarah*. It's something that produces something that's going to be
used as a type of—not even a תקרובת *tikroves* in some type
of religious ritual, but not even as an offering to the god.
So to me it sounds like he's just expanding the definition, that
this is not the biblical אשרה *asherah* for him, you know, unless
he knows something I don't know, which I'm sure he does. Did
he really say that מדרבנן you have to go destroy this whole
tree? Yeah, I don't know. Again, notice how we're not talking about
destroying the tree. But yeah, anyway. Presumably. Right, but again, we're sort
of ignoring that מצוה Mitzvah of destroying. Okay.
אמר מימר אמי לי סבי דפומבדיתא הלכתא כשמואל Amar Meimar ami lei
sabei dePumbedisa hilchasa keShmuel and the elders of Pumbedisa told me that
the law was like Shmuel. But again, I don't know if this
really means at some biblical level. I must say that I haven't
checked the Rambam. In two seconds, I'll see if how he frames
it, if he frames this as a like a biblical or as
a rabbinic thing or whatever. Let's take a look where it is.
ח' עבודה זרה ג'. Chet Avodah Zarah Gimmel. It looks like. Okay.
Let's take a look what Rambam says about this. הלכה Halacha
Rambam... ח' ג'. Chet Gimmel. Oh,
it's a big Rambam.
ח' עבודה זרה... Chet Avodah Zarah... maybe ד'? Daled? ד'. Daled.
Okay,
so first Rambam says if you remove the עבודה זרה avodah zarah
it becomes permissible like our
משנה. I don't see where the Rambam rules like שמואל.
I'll have to look this up. Oh, here. האילן שהיו עובדי כוכבים
משמרים את פירותיו ואומרים שהם מוכנים לעשות שכר לבית עבודה זרה פלוני
ועושים מהם שכר ושותים אותם ביום חגם הרי זה אילן אשרה... Ha-ilan
shehayu ovdei chochavim meshapmim es peirosav ve-omrim sheheim muchanim la-asos sheichar leveit
avodah zarah ploni ve-osim mehaim sheichar veshosim osam beyom chagam harei zeh
ilan ashera... מפני שסתמו שהוא אשרה ולפיכך עושים בפירותיו כך שזו היא
חוק של אשרה. mipnei shestamo shehu ashera u-lephichach osim be-peirosav kach she-zu
hi chok shel ashera. So Rambam just assumes that it doesn't mean
stam they just used it, but that again, Shmuel presumably understood that
that was a sign, that was something they specifically would do to
a tree that they would worship, is use the fruit to drink
this, to make
this beer to drink on their holiday. So again, it's not, it's
as they say in ישיביש Yeshivish language, it's a סימן siman not
a סיבה. sibah. Okay, this is an indicator that this is a
tree that is worshipped, but it is not by virtue of this
that it is forbidden. It's ultimately this just points to the fact
that he understood
that that meant that this tree is actually worshipped. Okay, let's take
a look now at the next משנה. Turn the עמוד, amud, turn
the
דף. daf. לא ישב בצלה. Lo yeshev betzilah. Okay,
don't sit in its shade. I have to tell you again, going
back to this issue of this בית עבודה זרה Beis Avodah Zarah
and how is it defined and so on in what, you know,
is it the thing that is worshipped itself, you know, again and
all these things about how they were then translated to Christianity and
to the church, you know, became all these issues of can you
walk by a church and benefit from the shade? Because if the
thing is forbidden in benefit, then you're sitting in its shade and
you're getting benefit from it. Don't sit in its shade. ואם ישב
טהור. Ve'im yashav tahor. But if you sat in the shade of
this tree you are טהור tahor because now we get to not
just a question of forbidden in benefit, but remember our עבודה זרה
avodah zarah, is treated as something that is טמא tamei and therefore
but of course something that's טמא tamei might be a problem if
you're directly under the, you know, the foliage, right, the awning of
the tree. But the גמרא Gemara is going to deal with the
following two cases. I might as well just tell you what the
גמרא Gemara is going to conclude. Okay, so here's your tree, like
my lovely picture. Anyway, I know it's a mushroom, whatever, fine.
I got to get a third grader to draw a tree. Anyway,
fine. Anyway, so there's the shade of directly it provides when the
sun is directly overhead.
I already drew the sun. And then there's the shade when the
sun is not directly overhead, right, this shade here. So basically what
we're going to be saying is if you're here, you're getting benefit
from the shade, but you're not טמא tamei because you're not actually
under the tree itself. If you're here, so this is forbidden but
you're not טמא. tamei. This is forbidden and you are טמא. tamei.
Okay, so
ואם ישב טהור. Ve'im yashav tahor. לא יעבור תחתיה. Lo ya'avor tachteha.
Don't walk under it. ואם עבר טמא. Ve'im avar tamei. And if
you did, you are טמא. tamei. היתה גוזלת את הרבים ועבר תחתיה
טהור. Haysah gozeles es harabim ve-avar tachteha tahor. Let's say, however, the
problem was was that the רשות הרבים reshus harabim was going here.
Okay,
and this part was actually, I don't know if anybody's ever had
neighbors, we had this growing up, whatever, their tree goes over your
property. It's a pain in the... yeah, it happens always. I know,
so here anyway, so this is unfair to the רבים. rabim. It's
sort of taking away their
air space. So because it's
invading the air space, it has no ability to make this forbidden
and therefore it's מותר. mutar. Now the interesting thing is, what happens
if that was there first and then the... Well, that's an interesting
question too. You know, but like what happened? The guy worshipped it.
So he worshipped it and it's sort of like he only made
that part forbidden, right? Because the other part he didn't have the
right to define, we define its status cause that was sort of,
you know, but let's say I don't know, it started this way
and then it grew, like you know, is the new stuff doesn't
have a name of a status of עבודה זרה avodah zarah because
it's encroaching on the property? It seems to be something like that.
It's strange though, the way the intersection of property rights and its
status. Okay, now לא ישב בצילה פשיטא, lo yeshev betzilah peshita, obviously
don't sit in its shade. Now אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, לא נצרכה
אלא לצל צילה, lo nitzrecha ela letzeltzilah, the shade of its shade.
Now shade doesn't give off a shade, but what Rashi says that
means is, or the Gemara's going to be clear, is that, you
know, if you think about this, if this is the tree, right,
and the tree is, I don't know, ten feet, okay, then there's
like the immediate shadow, which is, you know, ten feet, the exact
same length of the thing itself, and then when there's like a
real, it's at a real angle, you know, it can cast a
shadow that's much longer than the height of the thing itself. So
this is considered צילה tzilah and this is considered צל צילה. tzeltzilah.
Okay? So, all right, so לא נצרכה אלא לצל צילה, lo nitzrecha
ela letzeltzilah, that even this is considered getting הנאה, hana'ah, even though
it's not nearly like the same, you know, amount of shading as
the direct shadow.
Okay, and לצל צילה, letzeltzilah, מכלל דבצל קומתו אם ישב טמא, michlal
debetzel komato im yashav tamei, do you mean to tell me if
it's telling you that don't stand here but you're טהור, tahor, do
you mean to tell me when you stand here you're טמא? tamei?
So the Gemara says: לא דאפילו בצל קומתו נמי אם ישב טהור.
lo dafillu betzel komato nami im yashav tahor. No, no, no, you're
טהור tahor in all these cases. The Mishnah's just saying don't stand
here, even here it's forbidden, but in all these cases you're טהור
tahor if you're not directly under the tree itself. דאפילו בצל קומתו
נמי אם ישב טהור והא קמשמע לן, dafillu betzel komato nami im
yashav tahor veha kamashma lan, what it's telling you is דאפילו צל
צילה לא ישב. dafillu tzeltzilah lo yeshev. Don't even sit in this
area because that's getting הנאה. hana'ah. But if you sit in even
in the direct shade as long as you're not directly under the
tree itself, you're actually going to be טהור. tahor. You say בצל
קומתו, betzel komato, isn't that right underneath it? No, צל קומתו tzel
komato is the entire, if you're six feet tall, it's the six
foot shadow in front of you. But even if, okay. What would
be called like right under it? תחתיה. Okay. אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן לא נצרכה אלא לצל קומתו. Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan lo nitzrecha ela letzel komato. So he
actually says no, the opposite is the חידוש. chiddush. That it's saying
don't stand here, yes that's obvious that that means that you're not
allowed to get הנאה, hana'ah, but the חידוש is that even though
you're standing here, it's the same point, it's just he emphasizes that
the חידוש of the Mishnah's focusing on this. Even though you're standing
here you're still טהור. tahor. So the Gemara says: מכלל דבצל צילה
אפילו לכתחילה ישב, michlal debetzeltzilah afillu lechatchilah yeshev, does that suggest, if
the Mishnah's talking about this, does that suggest I'm allowed to sit
here? So the Gemara says: לא הא קמשמע
לן דאפילו בצל קומתו אם ישב טהור. lo ha kamashma lan dafillu
betzel komato im yashav tahor. No, it's basically the same point just
emphasizing the other side. You know, is the Mishnah saying don't sit,
even this is forbidden to sit, but of course you're טהור tahor
even here, that's one way to read the Mishnah, and the חידוש
is that even here it's forbidden. The other way to read the
Mishnah is even here you're still טהור tahor if you're not directly
under the tree, but of course it's also forbidden to sit here.
So same point. Don't sit in either of these spaces, it's getting
הנאה, hana'ah, but even in the closer space you're still טהור tahor
unless you're directly under the tree. ולא יעבור תחתיה ואם עבר טמא,
velo ya'avor tachteha ve'im avar tamei, don't go directly underneath it and
if so you're טמא. tamei. Now remember we said that the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah itself, this was what was ironic, was treated sort
of like a שרץ sheretz or a נדה, niddah,
and whereas something offered to an עבודה זרה avodah zarah was like
a מת. meit. So if it's a שרץ sheretz or a נדה,
niddah, you wouldn't be טמא tamei by being underneath a שרץ sheretz
or נדה, niddah, so it has to be the מת meit idea.
Well where's the מת meit idea if this is an אשירה? asheirah?
So מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אי אפשר דליכא תקרובת עבודה זרה, ee
efshar delika tikrovet avodah zarah, it's so ironic, right? Yes, the thing
itself is an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah. but that wouldn't make you
טמא tamei by walking underneath. The point is it's impossible if this
was an עבודה זרה avodah zarah presumably there have been things that
have been presented and offerings to the עבודה זרה avodah zarah that
are somewhere underneath the tree. Dig a little bit under the ground,
you'll find things that were offered. And if it's like a מת,
meit, then you're in the same, under the same roof as a
מת, meit, right? If offerings are exist, are placed at the base
of the tree and they're under the ground and you're standing here
and then the מת, meit, the טומאה tumah goes up and it
shades over you and you're טמא tamei like being in the house
of a
מת. meit. Okay, so מני, mani, who is this? רבי יהודה בן
בתירה היא, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira hee, דתניא רבי יהודה בן בתירה
אומר מנין לתקרובת עבודה זרה שמטמא באהל, detanya Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira
omer minayin letikrovet avodah zarah shemetammei be'ohel, how do you know it
causes טומאה tumah even under a roof? שנאמר ויצמדו לבעל פעור ויאכלו
זבחי מתים, shene'emar vayitzmedu le'baal pe'or vayochlu zivchei meitim, they ate the
sacrifice to the dead. מה מת מטמא באהל, mah meit metammei be'ohel,
the same way, so it's so funny because זבחי מתים, zivchei meitim,
the primary thing that is identified as the מת meit is the
עבודה זרה avodah zarah itself. The offerings are just offerings to the
dead, and nevertheless we only apply the status to the offering. מה
מת מטמא באהל אף תקרובת עבודה זרה מטמא באהל. mah meit metammei
be'ohel af tikrovet avodah zarah metammei be'ohel. I can't figure that out
for the life of me. Okay, היתה גזוזת הרבים ועבר תחתיה טהור,
haitah gezozat harabbim ve'avar tachteha tahor, if it was overshading the רשות
הרבים reshut harabbim then it, you are טהור tahor and presumably it's
also מותר muttar to. you're not getting הנאה, hana'ah, it's not considered
a transgression of הנאה, hana'ah, it has no right to define a
status of something that the רבים rabbim have property rights to. Says
the גמרא, Gemara איבעיא להו: ibaiah lehu: עבר או עובר? avar o
over? If you passed under it or you're even לכתחילה lechatchila allowed
to pass? Not, again, and presumably it doesn't mean that it's concerned
that it's forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, presumably it is permissible in הנאה.
hana'ah. It's totally permissible, but the question is that doesn't mean we
should let you do it, you know, it's a bad policy maybe
to let you do it, it just makes people think that it's
not a big problem or something. On the other hand, people need
to use רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So Rav Isaac ben Eleazar משמיה
דחזקיה mishmei d'Chizkiyah says עובר over לכתחילה lechatchila you can pass under
it. ורבי
יוחנן אמר אם עבר v'Rabbi Yochanan amar im avar if you passed.
ולא פליגי, v'lo peligi, הא דאיכא דרכא אחרינא הא דליכא דרכא אחרינא.
ha d'ika darcha achrina ha d'leika darcha achrina. The question is: do
you have another option? If you have another option, then you should
take the other option. What do you mean by other option? Let's
say it takes you forty-five minutes out of your way? So תוספות
Tosafot says it. Look at תוספות. Tosafot. אי דאיכא דרכא אחרינא, ei
d'ika darcha achrina, תוספות Tosafot says פירוש קצר כזה, perush katzar kaze,
just as equivalent of an option and it would have been just
as easy to have gone on another path. You know, ואי בעינן
למימר אפילו אורחא אחרינא v'ei ba'inan l'meimar afilu orcha achrina if you're
forced to go on a longer path, so אם כן אין לדבר
סוף, im kein ein ladavar sof, there's always another option, you know,
you could circumnavigate the globe in the opposite direction, right? You know,
you could always go a mile out of your way. So תוספות
Tosafot assumes it means, I know, you know, relatively equal. So if
you have an equivalent option. So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's
the issue. If you have an equivalent option, it's not good policy
to pass under an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah Okay. הא דאיכא דרכא
אחרינא הא דליכא דרכא אחרינא. ha d'ika darcha achrina ha d'leika darcha
achrina. But if there's, if it means you're going out of your
way, you don't have to, this עבודה זרה avodah zarah. has no
right to encroach on your, on the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Okay.
אמר ליה רב ששת לשמעיה, amar lei Rav Sheshet l'shamayei, רב ששת
Rav Sheshet who was blind, said to his attendant, and apparently they
were crossing through a space, a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, and they
knew there was an אשרה tree that overshaded it, and he said
to his attendant, כי מטית להתם ki matis l'hasam when you get
to that tree, ארהיטני, arhitani, rush me through, you know, make me,
let you know, have me go through quickly, I don't want to
tarry underneath the tree.
Okay. היכי דמי? heichi dami? So the גמרא Gemara says, what's the
case? אי דליכא דרכא אחרינא, ei d'leika darcha achrina, if there was
no other path, equivalent path, למה לי ארהיטני? lama li arhitani? Why
does he have to be rushed through? מישרא שרי, mishra shari, it's
permissible. ואי דאיכא דרכא אחרינא, v'ei d'ika darcha achrina, if there's another
path, כי אמר ארהיטני מי שרי? ki amar arhitani mi shari? Even
rushing through it doesn't help, you're supposed to go on the other
path. לעולם דליכא דרכא אחרינא, le'olam d'leika darcha achrina, fine, there's no
other path. So really you could take your time. ואדם חשוב שאני,
v'adam chashuv shani, but somebody of the stature of רב ששת, Rav
Sheshet, again, these are tend to be at this stage, it tends
to be policy issues, not technical questions of איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah,
so a person of רב ששת's Rav Sheshet status should not be
seen spending time under an עבודה זרה tree.
Okay. Moving on. So now we're focused, we've shifted the focus, we've
decided what type of things are אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, now we're
focusing on what defines הנאה. hana'ah. A little bit of טומאה, tumah,
but basically what defines הנאה. hana'ah. So let's look at the next
משנה.
This is for the... some people won't walk under a canopy of
a church? Yeah, that's what I said. This gets translated... so how
do people hold? I mean, how does like a modern orthodox view...
Yeah, I mean, that's, look,
I mean, there's first of all a question about do you consider
like, you know, Christianity עבודה זרה and so on. And then even
if you do, do you consider like, you know, these types of
things, like if all of these are because it's assumed that they
worship the house itself, right? That seems like a little bit of
a far jump to make that type of an assertion about a
church or so. Right, but there's pieces of idols on this pavement.
Exact... Well, that's the טומאה tumah issue. That's like more secondary, but
yeah. Anyway, but the general approach is yeah, it seems hard to
apply even if you, you know, apply some aspects of these הלכות
halachos to Christianity whatever, it seems that this is a bit of
an extreme. So you would walk under... I mean basically... Yeah, I
don't avoid if I'm... I mean, I avoid going into churches under
certain circumstances or whatever, but I don't avoid walking by a church
on a sunny day that I'll get the indirect shade of the...
No, but I mean some people build a canopy outside the church,
you know, to protect people from the rain. Oh, I see, oh,
oh. Yeah, I mean I think again that that's not even the
thing, like that's just a canopy attached to the church or whatever,
yeah, probably. Alright. זרע תחתיה ירקות בימות הגשמים. zara tachteha yerakos bimot
hageshamim. Now you got this tree.
So okay, this tree was worshipped, but now again, maybe I don't
know this is... it's not exactly clear who owns this ground, because
we just said before that if it's public ground, it can't make
it forbidden, but if you're planting there, you must own the ground.
I don't know, maybe you have... it's like a little bit unclear
to me what this scenario is that you have a right to
be planting in this ground.
I'm not exactly figuring this out. This is the גוי goy doing
it, then you can have the... Yeah, I don't know. You buy
them at the... try to sell them at the farmers' market. Maybe,
maybe he owns the ground and he's giving you the right to
plant in it or something like that. Anyway, so I'd have to
figure that one out, but anyway, somehow it's still forbidden and it
still makes the area underneath it forbidden, but you have a right
to plant and you can plant vegetables underneath it in the rainy
season because then it's actually not getting, you're not getting any benefit,
if anything it's preventing the little sunlight that you need, the shade
is not helpful now, and maybe it's even preventing the rain from
getting to it. So that's not helping you. אבל לא בימות החמה,
aval lo bimot hachama, but during the sunny season. You can't do
it because then it's providing you shade and you're getting benefit.
Okay, והחזירין v'hachazirin לא בימות החמה ולא בימות הגשמים. lo b'yemos hachamah
v'lo b'yemos hageshamim. And these חזירין chazirin which are... is that like
חזרת? chazeret? What does it... how does it translate the word? Lettuce.
Yeah, חזרת. chazeret. Right, lettuce neither because in the... because shade is
always good for them even in the winter and the rainy season.
Okay, רבי יוסי אומר אף לא ירקות בימות הגשמים מפני שהנביאה נושרת
עליהן והוה להן לזבל. Rabbi Yossi omer af lo yerakos b'yemos hageshamim
mipnei shehanvia nosheres aleihen v'havay lahen l'zevel. He says even in the
rainy season, it's true the shade isn't necessary, but you're still getting
benefit because the droppings off of the tree become manure, become fertilizer,
not manure, fertilizer. Okay, so you are getting benefit. So the גמרא
says like this, למימרא דרבי יוסי סבר זה וזה גורם אסור. l'meimra
d'Rabbi Yossi savar zeh v'zeh gorem assur. So the גמרא says let's
figure out this case. Why are the רבנן not concerned about the
leaves or whatever that become fertilizer? So the גמרא assumes it means
because there are two things that are contributing to the growth of
these vegetables. There's the actual nutrients in the soil and there's the
nutrients of the leaves that are falling down. So that's a זה
וזה גורם, zeh v'zeh gorem, two things that are doing equal
contribution, okay? It doesn't mean equal, but they're both contributing on the
same plane, they're both providing nutrient. Okay, so is that considered like
you're deriving benefit or not if they're both providing nutrients? Yeah, but
what I'm trying to say is it's for sure it's not on
the same plane. The soil is always there, but in terms of
the stuff that falls down, I don't know, it's not falling down
every day, here and there maybe. All right, so what you want
to ask, I mean there are questions you can ask. What percentage
is it producing? Is it זה יכול וזה יכול, zeh yachol v'zeh
yachol, זה אינו יכול וזה אינו יכול, zeh eino yachol v'zeh eino
yachol, what would it have done, you know, so those are a
lot of questions to ask. The גמרא often doesn't get into those
levels of details. Anyway, let's take a look. So the גמרא thinks
that that's the debate, that רבי יוסי... רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
it's a problem because it's contributing, and the רבנן say it's not
a problem because a lot of it is coming from the soil,
maybe even the majority like Michael's saying. רבנן אמרי זה וזה גורם
מותר, Rabanan amri zeh v'zeh gorem mutar, it's permissible. So one minute,
האיפכא שמעינן להו. ha'ipcha sham'inan lehu. We generally have... know that when
they debate this issue, they take the flip position. דתנן, d'isnan, we
taught in the משנה, רבי יוסי אומר שוחק וזורה לרוח או מטיל
לים. Rabbi Yossi omer shochek v'zoreh l'ruach o metil l'yam. If you
have an עבודה זרה and you have to destroy it, you, you
know, you grind it up and then you throw it into the
ocean and that's how you get rid of it.
אמרו לו אף הוא נעשה זבל. amru lo af hu na'aseh zevel.
No, because then the stuff can be washed, you know, blown onto
a field or washed ashore and become fertilizer. ונאמר לא ידבק בידך
מאומה מן החרם v'ne'emar lo yidbak b'yadcha me'umah min hacherem and you'll
be benefiting. So here's a case where he's... he's not concerned that
this stuff will be fertilizer to help things grow and the רבנן
are. So it seems like the exact same debate, a combination of
soil plus this stuff, and רבי יוסי is concerned and the רבנן
are not... רבי יוסי is not concerned and the רבנן are, so
they're reversing their positions. So the גמרא says קשיא דרבנן אדרבנן קשיא
רבי יוסי ארבי יוסי, kashya d'Rabanan a'dRabanan kashya Rabbi Yossi a'Rabbi Yossi,
they're both... each one of them is taking an opposite position of
what they took before. So the גמרא says I could have gotten
maybe half out of it. בשלמא דרבי יוסי אדרבי יוסי לא קשיא.
bishlama d'Rabbi Yossi a'dRabbi Yossi lo kashya. I can explain רבי יוסי
that he's not contradicting himself. Normally by the case of the tree
or whatever, he's concerned that it's contributing and you're getting benefit. But
התם, hasam, over there by grinding up the idol, דקאזיל לאיבוד מתיר,
d'ka'azil l'ibud mattir, where you're basically... your point is to destroy it
and get rid of it, so it's okay. The way תוספות Tosafos
explains what that means is it means like the likelihood that something
that you're basically throwing in the wind to destroy or throwing into
the Dead Sea is somehow going to lead to somebody to get
benefit, that's already a little far-fetched. That he's not concerned about. הכא
דלא קאזיל לאיבוד, hacha d'lo ka'azil l'ibud, here it's not in the
process of being destroyed. It's just stuff that falls off the tree
to the ground directly below it, so אסור, it's a problem. So
yes, זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is a problem for רבי
יוסי, but in the case of destroying an idol, that's too far-fetched.
אלא דרבנן אדרבנן קשיא, ela d'Rabanan a'dRabanan kashya, but the רבנן is
a problem because if they're not concerned with the case of the
leaves from the tree, why are they concerned with the destroying of
the idol and throwing it into the Dead Sea? איפוך. ifoch. So
the first answer is fine, reverse the positions. Okay, we'll say that
it's, you know, let's say we'll reverse our משנה. That רבי יוסי
is... that the רבנן... that רבי יוסי is not concerned like he's
not concerned with the idol and grinding it up, and the רבנן
are concerned when they're contributing. That's one way. ואי בעית אימא, v'ee
bayis eima, that's always the cheap out. ואי בעית אימא לא תיפוך.
v'ee bayis eima lo tifoch. Or if you say fine, don't reverse
it, I'll still make it work.
דרבי יוסי כדשנינן, d'Rabbi Yossi k'dashninan, רבי יוסי we explained when you're
destroying an idol and trying to get rid of it, he's not
afraid indirectly it'll lead to some benefit.
דרבנן, d'Rabanan, how about the רבנן? Why are the רבנן here not
concerned and over there they are concerned?
דאמר רב מרי בריה דרב כהנא, d'amar Rav Mari brei d'Rav Kahana,
like רב מרי Rav Mari the son of רב כהנא Rav Kahana
says, מה דמשביח באור פוגם בבשר. ma d'mashbiach b'ur pogem b'vasar. So
this is a case about, I don't want to get into the
details, but it's about certain types of an animal that has a
מום mum and are you when you're redeeming it and then what
are you allowed to do in order to... the more you let
somebody get full benefit from this animal if it was a קרבן
korban that had a blemish that they redeemed, then the more they're
going to... the greater its value and the more they'll redeem it
for. So the question was, are you going to allow the person
after it's been redeemed to flay the animal in a way that
completely removes the leather as one whole piece? Okay, and if so
it'll raise the cost of the... the value of the animal. So
and that for it'll get redeemed for more. On the other hand,
might it be considered like a type of a ביזיון, Bizayon, not
respectful treatment of the animal? So one of the arguments is, you
know what, it doesn't matter, because even if you'll make the leather
worth more, just what you gain by the leather you'll lose by
the way it'll damage the meat. Okay? So the point is it's
an offsetting type of a thing, alright? The specifics don't really matter.
הכא נמי, Hacha nami, משבח
בנביא פוגם בבשר. mashbiach binvia pogem bivsar. So here, yes, the rabbis
are concerned about זה וזה גורם. zeh v'zeh gorem. Everybody's concerned with
זה וזה גורם. zeh v'zeh gorem. Okay? But why here do they
allow the vegetables? Because they say the little that you gain by
the fertilizer is offset by the amount you lose by the shade.
The shade actually hurts it. So in the in the sort of
net you haven't gained by being under the tree. Which is actually
a fascinating idea because you might say why do I view things
in the net? Like if today for this five minutes I gain,
the sun wasn't out anywhere so being under the tree didn't hurt
it being in the shade, but you know how about overnight? Let's
look at every single night. The sun isn't out. So in the
night time I'm not being hurt by the shade and I am
gaining by the stuff that falls in the night time. So why
isn't it אסור every night time? Why do I get to look
at it in the macro and not in the micro? Right? I
think that's a big חידוש. Like if it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah,
every moment of getting הנאה hana'ah should be a problem. Anyway, but
that's how the גמרא explains it. Okay?
Fine. So that's it. Everybody holds זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
is a problem, and the question is about do you sort of
like look at it in the macro or not. And the Rabbis
look at it in the macro and they say it's not a
problem. וסבר רבי יוסי זה וזה גורם אסור? V'savar Rabbi Yosei zeh
v'zeh gorem assur? Does Rabbi Yosei really hold that זה וזה גורם
zeh v'zeh gorem is אסור? Okay, because now we're saying everybody holds
that.
והתנן, Vehatnan, רבי יוסי אומר נוטעין ייחור של ערלה ואין נוטעין אגוז
של ערלה. Rabbi Yosei omer notin yichur shel orlah v'ein notin egoz
shel orlah. You can plant a sapling of an ערלה orlah tree
because the saplings aren't forbidden. It's only the fruit that's forbidden. But
you can't plant a nut of an ערלה orlah tree because the
nut is forbidden. מפני שהוא פרי, mipnei shehu peri, because it's a
fruit. Okay? And then you're getting benefit from it. You're not allowed
to get benefit. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב מודה רבי יוסי שאם
נטע והבריך והרכיב מותר. V'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav modeh Rabbi Yosei
she'im nata v'hivrich v'hirkiv mutar. He agrees, however, that if you did
plant it and you then you know and you and you what
do you call it? Not pruned, grafted it, thank you, that it's
permissible. ותניא נמי הכי, V'tanya nami hachi, we even taught a ברייתא
Baraisa that way. מודה רבי יוסי שאם נטע והבריך והרכיב מותר. Modeh
Rabbi Yosei she'im nata v'hivrich v'hirkiv mutar. Now, why is it מותר?
mutar? Because the point is is that that becomes a type of
a זה וזה גורם. zeh v'zeh gorem. Now רש''י, Rashi I'll just
explain to תוספות Tosafot first, because תוספות Tosafot is insistent that when
we say זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is מותר, mutar, it
means that they have to be contributing in the same way. רש''י
says that the זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem in this case
is forget the grafting case. Here's your nut under the ground, okay?
It grows into a nice tree, okay? And so this is ערלה.
orlah. So what's the זה וזה גורם? zeh v'zeh gorem? Well, the
nut did part of it and the ground did part of it.
Okay? So that's זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem into that. תוספות
Tosafot says that's not זה וזה גורם, zeh v'zeh gorem, okay? Because
what the ground which is מותר mutar is contributing is very different
than what the nut is. This is the source of the tree;
these are the nutrients. So זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is
they have to be contributing on the same plane. So תוספות Tosafot
says no, here's the case. The case is is that basically you
planted this nut which you weren't you know this tree grew up.
Now this tree here is forbidden. That came from a forbidden nut
of ערלה. orlah. You took a branch from this tree
and now you grafted that branch onto this tree, okay? So that's
now and then a fruit grows from that, okay? So that's now
a זה וזה גורם. zeh v'zeh gorem. This is an ערלה orlah
branch right because it sort of came from an ערלה orlah so
it's getting הנאה hana'ah and this is a permissible thing and they're
both contributing to the fruit. Okay? So that's how תוספות Tosafot understands
it. Okay? But anyway, so רבי יוסי says it's permissible, so it
seems that זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is permissible. Okay? וכי
תימא שאני ליה לרבי יוסי בין שאר איסורין לעבודת כוכבים? V'chi teima
shani leh leRabbi Yosei bein shear issurin l'avodat kochavim? Maybe by עבודת
כוכבים he's strict and by other things he's more lenient. ומי שאני
ליה? U'mi shani leh? Where but but since when does he make
that distinction? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught a ברייתא: Baraisa: שדה שנטייבלה בזבל
עבודת כוכבים. Sadeh shenityabla b'zevel avodat kochavim. If you have a field
that has been—oh, שכוייח. shkoiyach. If you have a field that has
been sort of, you know, what do you call it, been fertilized
with the fertilizer of עבודת כוכבים, like an animal that was worshipped
or something of that nature,
וכן פרה שנתפטמה בכרשיני עבודת כוכבים, v'chen parah shenitpatma b'karshinei avodat kochavim,
or cow that's been fattened with type of a fodder that has
been that's forbidden הנאה, hana'ah, it's been worshipped or it's תקרובת עבודה
זרה tikrovet avodah zarah or whatever it is. So תניא חדא, tanya
chada, one ברייתא Baraisa teaches: שדה תזרע פרה תשחט, Sadeh tizarei, parah
tishacheit, that the thing remains permissible.
You plant the field, no problem. ותניא אידך, v'tanya idach, שדה תבור
ופרה תרזה. sadeh tivor v'parah tirazeh. No, you have to let the
field lay fallow and let the cow go skinny. Okay? That it's
a problem. I don't know exactly how that fully reverses it but
let's bracket that for now. If you don't use it, then you
can use the cow. That's what I said, so let's bracket that
for now. Yeah, but that's the point. מאי לאו הא רבי יוסי
והא רבנן? Mai lav ha Rabbi Yosei v'ha Rabbanan? So presumably... Presumably,
this is the debate. This is a case of זה וזה גורם.
zeh vezeh gorem. You fed it these forbidden foods, but it also
ate other good food. You fertilized it with this forbidden fertilizer, but
it also got good fertilizer. One says it's okay, one says it's
not okay, right? So, presumably, that's the debate, right? Presumably, that the
case that it's okay is רבי יוסי, that רבי יוסי, like the
ערלה orlah case, רבי יוסי really says זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh
gorem is okay. We see it by the ערלה, orlah, right? We
see he says that if you grafted it, it's okay. And here,
too, by the cow. And the ones that say it's no good
is the Rabbis. So, it sounds like a reasonable read of this
is to assume that there's this debate going on about זה וזה
גורם, zeh vezeh gorem, and it's all the same, whether you're dealing
with ערלה, orlah, whether you're dealing with עבודה זרה. Okay. So, ורבנן?
So, the גמרא says, לא הא רבי אליעזר, לא הא רבי אליעזר,
מאי לאו הא רבי יוסי והא רבנן? לא הא רבי אליעזר והא
רבנן. lo ha Rebbe Eliezer, lo ha Rebbe Eliezer, mai lav ha
Rebbe Yosi ve-ha Rabanan? Lo ha Rebbe Eliezer ve-ha Rabanan.
No, it's not רבי יוסי and the רבנן; it's רבי אליעזר Rebbe
Eliezer and the רבנן. And we will pause here in mid-sentence, but
anyway, we already got a little bit ahead, and we'll pick up
with this tomorrow. But what we're going to do is we're going
to say: is there a debate about זה וזה גורם? zeh vezeh
gorem? Yes, there is. But it is not the debate of רבי
יוסי and the רבנן. רבי יוסי and the רבנן all hold, as
we sort of explained until now, that זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh
gorem is a problem. Why do the רבנן let you plant under
the tree? Because it's in the macro; you're not getting הנאה. hana'ah.
But they all hold it's a problem. How about here, where it
seems clear by this case of the cow and the field that
somebody holds זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh gorem is okay? That's going
to be a different position. That's not רבי יוסי; that's going to
be a different position, and we will see that tomorrow. Okay, so
we'll stop there.